Hello and welcome to my video
on hemiacetals and acetals for
introductory organic chemistry.
So hemiacetals occur when an
alcohol adds to a carbonyl group.
And this can be one of the trickiest
reactions that allied health students
come across in their introductory
organic chemistry classes.
So i'm going to try my best to
try to break it down for you in
a very simple manner of really
what is occurring in the reaction.
So it all starts from
just a simple carbonyl.
So a carbonyl is anytime you have a
C double bonded to an oxygen and this
can come in the many different forms.
The specifically in this
reaction is whenever you have
an aldehyde and a ketone.
So whenever we have this carbonyl, it's
going to be reacting with an alcohol.
So if you remember from class,
that is an OH group that's attached
to some sort of R group, which
is an alkyl group or alkyl chain.
So when these two things meet,
what is really going to happen?
So let's try to dive into
it and go from step by step.
So if it all goes, let's
start with just an aldehyde.
Reacting with an alcohol and what
this is going to make is a hemiacetal
So if I take a aldehyde and an
alcohol, let's draw those out.
So if I take the C double bond O So
we have our carbonyl now What makes an
aldehyde is that it has a little hydrogen
on it and then that's going to be attached
to an R group And this is going to be
coming into contact with an alcohol.
So in order to show what exactly is
happening in this reaction, well we have
to try to remember electronegativity,
which comes from introductory chemistry
and really how all these different atoms
can have these little partial negative,
partial positive charges on them.
So if you can remember elements
like oxygen, nitrogen, fluorine,
these are always considered to
be slightly electronegative.
So they're always slightly negative.
So why don't we put that
little delta negative on there.
And then if you kind of remember
anything, anytime you have something
that's a little electronegative next
to something not so negative, well,
they're always going to be positive.
So things like hydrogen and carbon in
this case will be a little positive.
So, if you remember from intermolecular
forces, well, if I ever had a
hydrogen next to an oxygen, Well,
they're going to be making a
connection or an intermolecular force.
Same thing with this other oxygen
and carbon down here, right?
They're going to be
attracted to one another.
So when you have multiple attractions,
there's always a possibility for
bonds to create, especially when
it's favorable for the structure.
So this is how a hemiacetal
starts to form, okay?
So this is where the hemiacetal is
going to come into play and what
we're going to be doing is we're
going to be breaking two bonds and
we're going to be forming two bonds.
So, pal, let's show that.
So, for breaking, what we're
going to do is we're going to
show that with little red X's.
And then for forming, we're going to be
showing that with little purple arrows.
So the red X, what we'll see is we're
going to be breaking one of the carbon
oxygen bonds, notice how there's two.
from the double bond and then
we're also going to be breaking
the OH bond that is here.
So both those are going to break
and what they're going to do, it's
going to essentially, it's going
to be rotating around the molecule.
So what we're going to be doing
is we're going to show where
these new bonds are going to form.
So the arrows are showing where
that's going to be rotating around.
the molecule.
So, when that happens, we're going
to take this intermediate structure
that we have here, we're going to
copy and paste it down here, and show
how everything's going to be broken.
So, if everything with the red x's
is going to break, oops, we're going
to show that going away, little blue
dots are going to go away in the
process, and they're going to now be
replaced with little purple lines.
from before.
Okay, so that shows that, all
right, those little purple arrows,
they moved and they rotated.
So this is what we refer
to as our hemiacetal.
So we have our hemiacetal
structure that is here.
We can get rid of these little delta
pluses and minuses that we have here.
And we can show our
intermediate structure.
Now it looks a little funny, but that's
going to be the same thing as if I like,
let's just redraw it for ourselves.
So if we have a carbon with our
O H on one side and notice how we
have two oxygens connected to the
same carbon with a little hydrogen.
And then an R group.
Okay, so we have the little alkyl
groups that are attached here and it
has that signature like little googly
eyes look to it in its structure.
So this, though, is not the final step.
Hemiacetals are very unstable.
They tend to not want to be in
the structure all the time and the
reason behind that has to do with
with this little alcohol here.
It's something, as you kind of
noticed in the last step, caused the
whole reaction in the first place.
Well, the reaction is going to continue
because it wants to keep going.
So how do we get to the final step?
Well, it has to go from a
hemiacetal to an acetal.
So if this was, if we had step
one, we have our acetal here.
Now for step two, what we're going to
be showing is a condensation Reaction.
So in condensation, the whole idea is
that we're going to be Removing water.
So how do we remove water?
Well, whenever that is removed That's
something that's going to show that a
bond is going to be created So let's
take our hemiacetal from before And
what we're now going to do is we're
going to copy and paste it down here
And being that this is in a solution of
alcohol being an alcohol reacted with
this earlier We're going to now show
how we're going to be removing Water.
So if I draw an alcohol, so I have my OH
attached to an R group, and I'm going to
color in my H from my other structure.
Maybe you might see like, all
right, well, how is H2O removed?
Well, we have H2O that is right
here, and we can see that that's
going to be removed In the process.
So when that happens, it's almost
like taking a straw to a liquid
and sucking the liquid out of it.
And as a result, it's going to
vacuum and close it all together
and push it all closer together.
So when we have that, we're
going to redraw our structure.
Just like so.
And what we can now see is that
instead that purple line is now
going to be connected to the R group,
which was by that water earlier.
And the other part of the structure
is going to stay the same.
So now we have our signature look here
of two oxygens, so that's a little googly
eyes, both connected to the same carbon.
So we have, so if we want to
redraw that for ourselves, we can.
So we have our carbon with an oxygen,
two of them both pointing in different
directions, with an, with different
R groups potentially on each side.
Okay, so we have that look to
it, and this is what we refer
to as an acetal, all right?
So acetal is when it originates
from an aldehyde versus a ketal
is when it is from an aldehyde.
Okay, so let's sum all that up.
So that way we have it in one location.
What exactly is changing at
each of these different parts?
Well, let's go through it and try to see.
So just in summary, what
functional groups are changing?
Because this is one of those
different mechanisms you can
try to memorize for yourself.
So that way when you get to
biochemistry, and you're trying to
understand how carbohydrates form
with each other, we can try to
remember the different groups we had.
So if you remember in the beginning,
we started with a carbonyl.
That carbonyl, what
exactly did it turn into?
Well, if we go back up, we can see
that, okay, well, we had our carbonyl
here that I'm highlighting in blue.
And we can see that it
turned into an alcohol.
So that was step one.
The alcohol, the carbonyl, turned into...
and alcohol.
So why don't we draw that for
ourselves, let that step happen.
Then what happened to the
alcohol in the next step?
Well, let's try to follow it.
So if you remember from up here,
right, if this part was the part in
blue, as we can see from above, well,
that's when it turned into An ether.
So that entire step went from,
so in blue, went from carbonyl
to an alcohol to an ether.
Alright, what about the
other functional group?
What does happen with the alcohol?
Why don't we show that
one in a different color?
Why don't we pick um, let
me do pink for that one.
So the alcohol, let's write
that down for ourselves so we
can make notes for ourselves.
The alcohol went from what to what?
So if I go back to my original
structure, So let's follow the alcohol.
So we see, we have the OH
here now in the new structure.
We see that it changed to this ether here.
So it went from an alcohol to an ether.
Now let's see, did it do anything
in the, in the next step?
Well.
In the second step, well, let's see,
we still have an ether and it remains
the same, so it doesn't change.
So there's no, it only has to change once.
So that first step of the reaction
is really the hardest part.
So, but however, we can break it
down for ourselves as seeing that.
All right, well, this went from
an ether or alcohol to an ether.
And then in step two, there was no change.
So why don't we label that as
ones and twos for ourselves.
So we can really see, and then
we can write no change, alright?
So, in summary, this alcohol
was added to this carbonyl, and
eventually we made a hemiacetal.
We'll say hemis, because
that's our halfway point.
So our acetal, and then it went
to a full blown acetal in the end.
Now, just as a reminder, even though
I did not show it, a ketone can also
go through this reaction as well.
And in that case, that would go from,
so if before it was an aldehyde.
So if we have a ketone,
it'll turn into a hemiketal.
So K E T A L, and eventually it'll
go through a same to its final step.
Now, how can you tell the
difference between the two?
Well, it's actually really
quite easy to do, is if you
look at your final structure.
Notice how, if we look at the carbon where
both the little oxygens are connected
to, we see that there's a hydrogen here.
What is something that's on the aldehyde
structure in the very beginning?
Well, go back.
If you look at an aldehyde, notice
how it had its hydrogen here.
So if you see a hydrogen at the very end,
that's how you can tell it's an acetal.
Versus if it's a ketone,
there will not be a hydrogen.
So, there's a lot of little
things to take care of.
Feel free to watch this video
as many times as you want.
Hopefully it helps.
And if you liked what you saw, please
consider liking and subscribing
and commenting for future videos.
Thank you, and I hope
this helped a little bit.
Alright, I'll see you all later.
This is Dr.
Dan, and please come by for future videos.